<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-06-26T23:00:09-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Aditya Sengupta</title><subtitle>Personal website for Aditya Sengupta.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Projects</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/06/26/projects.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Projects" /><published>2020-06-26T16:25:17-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-26T16:25:17-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/06/26/projects</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/06/26/projects.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;ulab-physics-and-astronomy-curriculum&quot;&gt;ULab Physics and Astronomy: Curriculum&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am the 2020-21 curriculum chair for the Physics and Astronomy Division of Undergraduate Lab @ Berkeley, an organization that introduces students to techniques and skills used in physics research. I am writing and supervising the creation of modules on introductory programming for science, Git, research literacy, LaTeX, and academic communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ULab github=&quot;&quot; org=&quot;&quot;&gt; (screenshot of Stats Module 1)

## ULab Physics and Astronomy: Mentorship
In 2019-20, I was a mentor for ULab, advising a group of five students on a project we named ABRA, for Accessible Balloon RAdiometer. We aimed to detect the cosmic microwave background and to fit its spectrum to that of a blackbody, using off-the-shelf electrical components and custom PCBs. Progress was unfortunately halted due to the COVID-19 pandemic.
Poster | &lt;link to=&quot;&quot; presentation=&quot;&quot; /&gt;

## Space Technologies and Rocketry
I helped establish the Simulations subteam for STAR, UC Berkeley’s high powered rocketry team, and was its first deputy lead. I identified simulation needs across the five other technical subteams, established the workflow for integrating simulations (in Solidworks, ANSYS, and first-principles code) into the team’s design cycle, and led workshops on running simulations and created the associated documentation.
Github for my first-principles rocket simulation

## Custom LaTeX
I use LaTeX for all my course notes and homework assignments, and I’ve packaged my custom environments and style so they can be easily imported into a new TeX file.
Github
&lt;/ULab&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">ULab Physics and Astronomy: Curriculum I am the 2020-21 curriculum chair for the Physics and Astronomy Division of Undergraduate Lab @ Berkeley, an organization that introduces students to techniques and skills used in physics research. I am writing and supervising the creation of modules on introductory programming for science, Git, research literacy, LaTeX, and academic communication. (screenshot of Stats Module 1)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Research</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/06/26/research.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Research" /><published>2020-06-26T16:25:17-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-26T16:25:17-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/06/26/research</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/06/26/research.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;tip-tilt-control&quot;&gt;Tip-Tilt Control&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worked with Dr. Rebecca Jensen-Clem on an improved algorithm to control the tip and tilt modes of adaptive optics telescope systems. I discussed the work at the Center for Adaptive Optics Fall Retreat, 2019, and am currently working on testing the algorithm on an AO testbench.
Github | Poster | Presentation slides&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pyramid-wavefront-sensor&quot;&gt;Pyramid Wavefront Sensor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worked with Dr. Rebecca Jensen-Clem on creating a simulation of the pyramid wavefront sensor at Keck II, towards demonstrating that predictive wavefront control would create the expected reduction in wavefront residuals. I presented the work at the UC Berkeley Astronomy Poster Summer Intern Symposium in 2018.
Github | Poster&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ffast-and-spright&quot;&gt;FFAST and SPRIGHT&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I worked with Orhan Ocal and Prof. Kannan Ramchandran on the FFAST and SPRIGHT algorithms to compute sample- and time-efficient DFTs and Walsh-Hadamard transforms, to make algorithm improvements based on coding theory, investigate the effect of hyperparameters, and make a Python implementation of the algorithms for ease of use.
FFAST Github | SPRIGHT Github&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;occurrence-rates&quot;&gt;Occurrence Rates&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am currently investigating exoplanet occurrence rate models with Prof. Courtney Dressing, to improve upon estimates of the architecture and frequency of planetary systems around other stars using forward modeling based on data from NASA’s Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite.
Github&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Tip-Tilt Control I worked with Dr. Rebecca Jensen-Clem on an improved algorithm to control the tip and tilt modes of adaptive optics telescope systems. I discussed the work at the Center for Adaptive Optics Fall Retreat, 2019, and am currently working on testing the algorithm on an AO testbench. Github | Poster | Presentation slides</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Teaching and Notes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/06/26/teaching.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Teaching and Notes" /><published>2020-06-26T16:25:17-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-26T16:25:17-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/06/26/teaching</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/06/26/teaching.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;teaching&quot;&gt;Teaching&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;eecs-126-probability-and-random-processes&quot;&gt;EECS 126: Probability and Random Processes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will be a TA for EECS 126 in Fall 2020, and in Spring 2020 I designed the Kalman Filtering lab assignment, walking students through the implementation and applications of the Kalman filter. (picture of that)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;link to=&quot;&quot; current=&quot;&quot; teaching=&quot;&quot; notes=&quot;&quot; page=&quot;&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;math-53-multivariable-calculus&quot;&gt;Math 53: Multivariable Calculus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was a Math 53 Study Group Facilitator at the UC Berkeley Student Learning Center in Spring 2020. I designed worksheets for and taught a twice-weekly problem solving study group section, as well as teaching midterm and final review sections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;link to=&quot;&quot; worksheets=&quot;&quot; /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tutoring&quot;&gt;Tutoring&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been working at the Student Learning Center as a mathematics tutor since Spring 2018, and have also tutored for CS 61BL, Data Structures and Programming Methodology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;expository-papers-and-course-notes&quot;&gt;Expository Papers and Course Notes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like creating notes on content that I learn about (from my classes or otherwise) and that I’d like to understand better. This section includes a few of these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My super-compact cheat sheet for CS 189, Introduction to Machine Learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An informally-written introduction to Jordan canonical form, introduced in Math 110&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An introduction to adjoints and inner product spaces, also for Math 110&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My proof of the Central Limit Theorem, from when I was taking EECS 126&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A (hopefully intuitive) partial guide to introductory analysis, written while auditing Math 202A&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A near-direct transcription of two Physics 5A lectures, introducing special relativity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A guide to Einstein summation notation born out of my complete confusion in the first Physics 105 lecture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A very informally written response to a friend misunderstanding limits when we were 14&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, here are my course notes from many of the classes I’ve taken at Berkeley!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Math: Calculus II, Multivariable Calculus, Linear Algebra and Differential Equations, Introduction to Abstract Algebra, Introduction to Analysis, Linear Algebra II
Physics: Introductory Thermo/Quantum, Analytic Mechanics, Electromagnetism and Optics (partial), Quantum Mechanics I, Quantum Mechanics II (partial)
EECS: Signals and Systems, Feedback Control Systems, Optical Engineering&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I have not included my EECS 126 course notes as I hope to instead use them to contribute to the class’s official notes.)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Teaching</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Jekyll!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/06/26/welcome-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Jekyll!" /><published>2020-06-26T16:25:17-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-26T16:25:17-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/06/26/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2020/06/26/welcome-to-jekyll.html">&lt;p&gt;You’ll find this post in your &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll requires blog post files to be named according to the following format:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YEAR-MONTH-DAY-title.MARKUP&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YEAR&lt;/code&gt; is a four-digit number, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;MONTH&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DAY&lt;/code&gt; are both two-digit numbers, and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;MARKUP&lt;/code&gt; is the file extension representing the format used in the file. After that, include the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Hi, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'Tom'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home&quot;&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt; for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. If you have questions, you can ask them on &lt;a href=&quot;https://talk.jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll Talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">You’ll find this post in your _posts directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run jekyll serve, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.</summary></entry></feed>